Register to The Harold Rome Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Music by Rome, 1935-1981; Series I; 24.2' (58 boxes)
  - Stage Works, I.A
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1968-1969; 1 manuscript score (37 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 32, Folder 218)
      Includes copies of onionskins, pencil sketch of "Tara," and pencil sketch and lyrics ([2] sheets; typescript) for "New day on the way"
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1969; 1 manuscript score (45 p. in various pagings); 32-36 cm. (Box 32, Folder 219)
      Holographs, signed, and manuscript (photocopies) with markings
      Note on folder: 18 Scarlett Extra copies of piano scores from the original rehearsal score - Oct 1959 [i.e. 1969]
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1969-1972; 1 manuscript score (119 p. in various pagings); 33 cm. (Box 32, Folder 220)
      Holographs, in part, signed, in pencil (in part, photocopies)
      Includes holograph and published scores, sketches, and lyrics ([69] sheets; holographs in pencil)
      Notes on discarded envelope: notes + manuscript fall 1971-July 1972 GWTW / GWTW original ms - Marrying for fun, It doesn't matter now, How often, Scarlett counter melody, Tara
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1970 Feb.-Apr; 1 manuscript score (14 p. in various pagings); 32-34 cm. (Box 32, Folder 221)
      Includes scores, sketches, and lyrics ([2] sheets; holographs in pencil), and production lists [copies also with Production Materials]
      Note on discarded folders: old work sheets
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1971-1973; 1 manuscript score (72 p. in various pagings); 31-33 cm. (Box 32, Folder 222)
      Holographs, signed, in pencil and manuscript (in part, photocopies)
      Includes scores, sketches, and lyrics ([7] sheets; holographs in pencil)
      Note on discarded envelope: Work sheets + originals discarded for American production GWTW June-Sept. 1973; Harold Rome Personal; Brand New Friends, GWTW versions, How Lucky, Today's the Day
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1972; 1 manuscript score ([43] p. in various pagings); 28-33 cm. (Box 32, Folder 223)
      Holograph and manuscript (photocopy), in part printed
      Note on discarded binder: GWTW 1972 London
      Lyrics ([28] sheets; typescript), list labeled "New Lyrics (holograph in pencil), and list of musical numbers (typescript with pencil additions) laid in
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1972-1973; 1 manuscript score (334 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 33, Folder 224-226)
      Manuscript (photocopy) with pencil markings, holograph in pencil, and printed music, in part signed
      Note on discarded folder: Trude Reference L.A. Summer 1973 GWTW
      Printed music includes Japanese + English lyrics
      Some musical numbers marked "obsolete"
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1972-1973; 1 manuscript score (36 p. in various pagings) ;31 cm. (Box 33, Folder 227)
      Note on discarded envelope: original mss for American production
      "Notes to Joe Layton: Musical Cuts" ([4] sheets; typescript) laid in (copy filed with Production Materials)
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections], 1973; 1 manuscript score (39 p. in various pagings); 28-36 cm. (Box 33, Folder 228)
      Holographs, signed (in part, photocopies) in pencil
      Includes scores, sketches, and lyrics ([1] sheet; typescript)
      Also includes correspondence and production materials (copies, originals housed with respective series)
      Note on discarded envelope: Extra piano music L.A. Aug. 1973 more worksheets proofs of published arrangements
    - [Gone with the wind. English; Selections], 1 manuscript score (20 p. in various pagings); 30-33 cm. (Box 33, Folder 229)
      Holographs, signed, in pencil, and manuscript (photocopy)
      Includes miscellaneous scores, sketches, and lyrics ([8] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Rome's notes from discarded folder concerning this group of music laid in
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections; arr.], [ca. 1972]; 271 parts; 32 cm. (Box 34, Folder 230-241, Box 35)
      Manuscript in ink (photocopies and originals) with markings
      Arranged for orchestra
      Parts grouped as found, by musical number
      Parts all found in discarded envelopes labeled "London"
    - [Gone with the wind. English. Selections (Sketches)], [20] p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 35, Folder 242)
      Includes 2 scores for voice and piano as well as lyrics ([32] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Originally found with sketches for Southpaw
    - [Gone with the wind. A time for healing. English; arr.] A time for healing / Harold Rome; Orchestration by Bill Brohn. -- 1976., 1 manuscript score (10 p.) + 30 parts; 32-48 cm. (Box 94)
      Manuscript in pencil [score] and manuscript (photocopies) [parts]
      Arranged for voice and orchestra
      Copy of address label from folder laid in
    - [Harold Rome show] Harold Rome Show / Words and Music by Harold Rome. -- 1967-1968., 1 manuscript score (90 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 35, Folder 243-244)
      Manuscript in ink on onionskin
      For voice with piano accompaniment
      Includes duplicates (photocopies) and lyrics ([5] sheets; typescript)
      Note on discarded folder: 4/67 Harold Rome Show (Toujours Forever) Pink Deshons + transposition demos + extra music copies
      Contents [in order in which they were found]: Hindu Hula Hula. Public Image Verse. Public Image Refrain + Patter. If You Should Ask Me. Living Alone. Amanda. How! Pink Rhapsody. In The Pink. Drop In. An Intelligent Conversation. A Long Long Way. The Soft Of A Hand Verse. Everybody's Got To Do Their Thing. Hindu Hula Hula. Every Morning. I've Got A Feeling. Again.
    - [Howe and Hummel] H + H. -- 1963-1965., 1 manuscript score (85 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 35, Folder 245)
      Note on discarded folder: Howe + Hummel original
      Contents [in order in which they were found]: If love. Teddy boy. Penny. Where the girls are. New York. The least they could do. Let's talk about a woman. Broads and booze. Opening. Another day. Silver and gold. Abe. For no reason at all. New York the world's home town. Living alone. Living alone. Another day - another dollar. A long long way. Pretty little white house. A mother's heart. Honest John (lyrics laid in). A miracle. That's the law (lyrics laid in). A beautiful girl is like a beautiful girl
    - [Howe and Hummel] Howe and Hummel / Words and Music by Harold Rome. -- ca. 1965 Jan. 4., 1 manuscript score (115 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 35, Folder 246)
      Lyrics for two songs ([2] sheets; typescript) dated 1965 Jan. 4 laid in
      Contents [unnumbered songs at end]: 1 Opening. 2 Another day, another dollar. 3 If love. 4 Once too long ago. 5 New York. 6 Where the girls are. 7 The tragedy of Honest John. 8 Broads and booze. 10 The least they could do (is give me you). 11 Penny (duet). 12 Teddy boy. The world's home town (New York). Where the girls are. Pretty little white house. Silver and gold. That's the law. High society. A mother's heart. A long long way. For no reason at all. Another day - another dollar.
    - [Howe and Hummel] Howe and Hummel / Words and Music by Harold Rome. -- ca. 1965 Jan. 4., 1 manuscript score (71 p. in various pagings), bound; 32 cm. (Box 36, Folder 247)
      Photocopy of the above onionskin score with the addition of "Let's talk about a woman" where number 9 would be
    - [Howe and Hummel. Selections], ca. 1965 Jan. 4; 1 manuscript score (102 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 36, Folder 248)
      Manuscript (photocopies) and holographs, signed, in pencil
      Includes photocopies of onionskin score, holograph scores, sketches, and lyrics ([2] sheets; typescript)
    - [Howe and Hummel (Sketches)], 1963-1965; [42] p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 36, Folder 249)
      Also includes lyrics ([156] sheets; 28-32 cm., holographs in pencil and typescript) and a script dated 1965 Jan. 2
      Discarded folder labeled "worksheets 1963-64"
    - [Howe and Hummel (Sketches)], 1962-1963; [69] sheets of music; 32 cm. (Box 36, Folder 250-251)
      Also includes lyrics ([127] sheets; 28-32 cm., typescript and holographs in pencil), 3 scripts, historical notes and reprints of newspaper articles concerning Howe and Hummel, a letter from Joe Heller (typed letter signed, 1963 May 20) with a synopsis enclosed, and a copy of a letter from Rome to "Diana" (typed letter, 1963 Feb. 14) with a story line enclosed (copies of both letters and their enclosures are filed with Correspondence)
      Holographs, in part signed, in pencil
      Includes scores for voice with piano accompaniment
      Note on discarded envelope: H + H Early worksheets + mss.
    - [I can get it for you wholesale. Selections. Vocal score], 1 manuscript vocal score (7, 8 p.); 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 252)
      Includes "Somebody else" and "A funny thing happened"
      Note on discarded envelope: Deshons for "Wholesale"
    - [I can get it for you wholesale. Vocal score] Wholesale: Preliminary rehearsal score. -- 1961 Oct. 1., 1 manuscript vocal score (105 p. in various pagings), bound; 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 253)
      Contents: Somebody else. The way things are. When Gemini meets Capricorn. I'm not a well man. Momma, momma! The sound of money. The family way. Too soon. Who knows. Loyal, firm and true (the union song). Have I told you lately. Ballad of the garment trade. The bar mitzvah song. Miss Marmelstein. Grab them while you can. Love is not enough. Eat a little something. A funny thing happened.
    - [I can get it for you wholesale. Vocal score] I can get it for you wholesale: Final rehearsal score. -- 1961 Dec. 22., 1 manuscript vocal score (105 p. in various pagings), bound; 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 254)
      Contents: Somebody else. The way things are. When Gemini meets Capricorn. I'm not a well man. Momma, momma! The sound of money. The family way. Too soon. Who knows. Have I told you lately. Ballad of the garment trade. A gift today (The bar mitzvah song). Miss Marmelstein. What's in it for me? A funny thing happened. What are they doing to us now. Eat a little something.
    - [I can get it for you wholesale. Vocal score] I can get it for you wholesale / Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome; Book by Jerome Weidman based on his novel; Piano reduction by Robert H. Noeltner. -- N.Y.: Florence Music Company, Inc., c1963., 1 vocal score (203 p.), bound; 31 cm. (Box 37, Folder 255-256)
      Pl. no.: 5502-199
      Two copies
    - [In the pink], c1955; 1 manuscript score (93 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 257)
      Note on discarded envelope: Old In the Pink Deshons
      Contents [in order in which they were found]: Starlight, star bright. Miss O'Brien. Me and mom. Come to me! (The Molly Blood waltz). Watchout (for those girls in St. Louis). Opening. My I.B.M. and I. Molly! Con Chem hymn. Con Chem can make life beautiful. Land of might have been. The long haul. Executive conference. Come to me. What ever happened to Miss O'Brien. We're in love with a Con Chem dealer. Save it for the customers. Let's talk about a woman.
    - [In the pink. Boxes] Boxes / Harold Rome. -- 1968 Jun. 18., 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 37, Folder 258)
      Lyrics ([1] sheet; typescript) laid in
    - [In the pink. Boxes] Boxes / Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score (4 p.); 31 cm. (Box 37, Folder 259)
    - [In the pink. Come to me], Come to me / Harold Rome. 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 259)
    - [In the pink. Pink] Pink / Harold Rome. -- c1977., 1 manuscript score (5 p.); 32 cm. (Box 37, Folder 260)
      Lyrics (2 sheets; typescript) laid in
      Signed pencil sketch ([4] p.) and libretto and several lyrics ([49] sheets; typescript) laid in
      Note on discarded folder: In The Pink - new preliminary score
    - [In the pink. Selections], 1947-1955; 1 manuscript score ([123] p.); 31 cm. (Box 37, Folder 261-262)
      Includes 5 sketchbooks and lyrics ([3] sheets; typescript)
      Correction (2015): One notebook in Folder 262 appears to be associated with Operation Spring, rather than In the pink.
    - [In the pink. Selections], 1955 Apr.-Jun; 1 manuscript score ([60] p.), bound; 31 cm. (Box 37, Folder 263)
      Includes sketches
    - [In the pink (Sketches)], ca. 1967; [178] p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 38, Folder 264-265)
      Holographs, in part signed, in pencil and manuscript (photocopy)
      Includes lyrics ([227] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Some sketches labeled "Toujours"
      Note on discarded envelope: In the Pink work sheets
    - [Jonathan the wild. Selections], 1 manuscript score (61 p. in various pagings); 28-33 cm. (Box 38, Folder 266)
      Holographs in pencil (in part, photocopies) and manuscript (photocopies)
      Includes melodies, some with chord symbols in Rome's hand, and scores for voice with piano accompaniment with music by Lalo Schifrin and lyrics by Rome
      Note on discarded folder: Jonathan the Great
      Contents [in the order in which they were found]: Born to be great. London town. Don't trust your mother. I must have her. Thieves. Hanging. What am I doing. Who needs love. Jonathan the great. How many times. Wonderful friends. The bee. I must have her. That's the law. Brotherhood of thieves. Let's make Father happy. If you must ask. Hanging. London town. Farewell. Wond'rous day. Jonathan the great. Let's make Father happy.
    - [Let freedom sing. Johnny is a hoarder!] Johnny Is A Hoarder! / Music + Lyrics [by] Harold J. Rome., 1 manuscript score (5 p.); 32 cm. (Box 38, Folder 267)
    - [Little dog laughed. Happily ever after] 9 Happily ever after: from The little dog laughed / music & lyric by Harold J. Rome., 1 manuscript score ([4] p.); 34 cm. (Box 38, Folder 268)
      Holograph, signed, in ink with pencil additions
      With: Interlude to Happily Ever After ([4] p.)
    - [Man and wife] Man and wife / by Harold Rome. -- 1962 May-Oct., 1 manuscript score (87 p.); 32 cm. (Box 38, Folder 269)
      For voice with piano accompaniment (never orchestrated?)
      Note on discarded loose-leaf binder: Man + Wife original manuscript
      Some musical numbers labeled "Marriage Suite"
      Contents: 1 Prologue. 1a Introduction - Trio. Scene (1) (Shall I wear). Scene 2 (I remember). 2nd commercial. Scene 3 (Conversation - Albert and Cora). Scene 4 (I owe most of all). Anniversary scene (I owe most of all). Scene 5 Cora's solo. 4th Commercial. Scene 6 Is that a new dress. End of is that a new dress. Trio interruption. After Change places. In spite of my faults.
    - [Man and wife] Man and wife: An operetta entertainment in six scenes and four commercials / by Harold Rome. -- 1962., 1 manuscript score (123 p.), bound; 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 270-271)
      Three copies, all signed by Rome, one includes a more detailed table of contents ([2] sheets; typescript)
      Contents: Prologue. First commercial. Scene I (Shall I wear). Scene II (I remember). Second commercial. Scene III Conversation. Third commercial. Scene IV (I owe most of all). Scene V Cora's solo. Fourth commercial. Scene VIa (Is that a new dress). Scene VIb (After new dress). Scene VIc (Trio interruption). Scene VId (After change places). Scene VIe (In spite of my faults)
    - [Michael Todd's peep show. Gimme the shimmy!] Gimme the shimmy! / Music + Lyrics [by] Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 272)
    - [Mr. Brink] "Mr. Brink" / Words and Music by Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score (90 sheets in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 273-274)
      Note on first page: New version
      Note on discarded folder :"Deshons" and early prints
      Photocopies of onionskins, some with markings, laid in
      Contents: Come with me. The way of the world. The Pismire song. Practice makes perfect. Julian Northrup. Bird stuffer. Don't say it, Demmie. Do it here! Wonderful things. The wonder of the world. He can't come down. Mr. Brink. Evening time. The growing up song. The bughouse march. Come with me. Off to glory. I'll be good to Pud (incomplete)
    - [Mr. Brink] "Mr. Brink" / Words and Music by Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score (80 p. in various pagings), bound; 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 275)
      Note on cover: Mr. Brink (On Borrowed Time) Preliminary score
      Note on discarded envelope: Brink (The wonder of the world)
      Contents: Come with me. The Pismire song. Practice makes perfect. Julian Northrup (Introduction to "Birdstuffer"). Bird stuffer. Don't say it, Demmie. Do it here! Evening time. Wonderful things. Wonder of the world. He can't come down! Mr. Brink. Way of the world. The growing up song (When he grows up). The bughouse march. I'll be good to Pud. Sketches and scores ([10] sheets; holographs (photocopies)) laid in include: Oh, Miss Nellie. Fumadiddle. I'm glad there's you. Bittersweet
    - [Mr. Brink. Selections], 1962-1964; 1 manuscript score (92 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 276-277)
      Holographs, in part signed, in pencil and manuscript (photocopies)
      Includes sketches, lyrics ([85] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript), and a script (Book by Paul Osborn from his play "ON BORROWED TIME"; Music and Lyrics by Harold Rome)
      Some numbers labeled "discarded" and "On Borrowed Time"
    - [Mr. Brink. Selections], 1962-1977; 1 manuscript score (42 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 278)
      Includes sketches and lyrics ([1] sheet; typescript)
    - [Nantucket. I knew you well (Sketches)] I knew you well / Harold Rome., [2] p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 39, Folder 279)
    - [On borrowed time. Selections], 1961-1963; 1 manuscript score ([85] p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 279)
      Holographs, in part signed, in pencil and ink
      Includes sketches and lyrics ([82] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Note on discarded envelope: On Borrowed Time work sheets Jan-June 1963 and old original manuscripts
      Several scores and lyrics labeled "Mr. Brink" and "Picture Suite"
    - [On borrowed time. Selections], 1962-1963; 1 manuscript score ([42] p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 280)
      Includes sketches, and lyrics ([30] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Note on discarded folder: On Borrowed Time work sheets
    - [On borrowed time. Selections], 1963 Mar.-Sep; 1 manuscript score (56 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 281)
      Note on discarded envelope: On Borrowed Time old original manuscripts
      Several scores labeled "Mr. Brink"
    - [Op Pop (Sketches)], 1966 May-Jun; [31] p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 282)
      Includes lyrics ([47] sheets; holographs in pencil)
      Note on discarded folder [with other sketches]: work sheets 1966-Mar 1967 Wonderful Door / Southpaw
    - [Operation spring. Funny feeling] Funny feeling / Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 283)
    - [Operation spring. Gin rummy rhapsody] Gin Rummy Rhapsody., 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 283)
      Note on title page: Orig + deshon
      Pencil sketch on back
    - [Operation spring. Whatcha doing to me spring] Spring / Harold Rome., 1 manuscript score ([3] p.); 31 cm. (Box 40, Folder 283)
      Holograph, signed, in black and red pencil
      Pencil sketch on cover
    - [Operation spring]
      See also Box 37, Folder 262 (listed under In the pink).
    - [Pins and needles. Men, awake! Vocal score] Men, Awake! / Lyrics + Music by Harold J. Rome. -- c1936., 1 manuscript vocal score ([3] p.); 30 cm. (Box 40, Folder 284)
      Holograph, signed, in ink
    - [Pins and needles. Sing me a song with social significance. Vocal score] Sing me a song with social significance / Lyrics + Music by H.J. Rome. -- 1935 Oct., 1 manuscript vocal score ([3] p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 284)
    - [Pins and needles. Sing me a song with social significance] Sing me a song with social significance / Words and Music by Harold J. Rome. -- N.Y.: Mills Music Inc., c1937., 1 vocal score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 40, Folder 284)
    - [Pins and needles. Sunday in the park. Vocal score] Sunday in the park / Words and Music by Harold J. Rome. -- N.Y.: Mills Music Inc., c1937., 1 vocal score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box 40, Folder 284)
    - [Selections (Sketches)], 1960-1977; [108] p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 285-286)
      Holographs, in part signed, in pencil (in part photocopies)
      Includes scores for voice with piano accompaniment and lyrics ([135] sheets; holographs in pencil and typescript)
      Contents: "Coming home again," and two groups of sketches. First group; note on discarded envelope "worksheets 1963-1964" and contains sketch for Picture Suite, Harold Rome's Gallery, Mr. Brink / On Borrowed Time, Southpaw, and Howe and Hummel. The second group; note on discarded envelope "Discarded work sheets and music 1965-76-77" and includes sketches for Waltz of Love, Southpaw, Nantucket, In the pink, Wee bit o'scotch, Howe and Hummel, Impasse, Gone with the Wind, and Pins and Needles
    - [Sing out the news. Congressional minstrels] Congressional Minstrels / Words and Music by H.J. Rome., 1 manuscript score (6, [2], 5 p.); 34 cm. (Box 40, Folder 287)
      Holograph, signed, in ink with pencil markings
      Contents: A (Opening and Closing Song). B Song No 2 Dear Mr. President. E (Mammy Song).
    - [Sing out the news. Floradora] Sing out the news. Floradora. -- 1938., 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 32 cm. (Box 40, Folder 287)
      Manuscript in ink with pencil additions
      Stamp at end: Joseph Skolovsky Sep 7 1938 No. 17 Local 77
    - [Sing out the news. One of these fine days] One of These Fine Days / Words + Music by Harold J. Rome., 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 34 cm. (Box 40, Folder 287)
    - [Sing out the news. Sing ho! For private enterprise] Sing Ho! For Private Enterprise: From "Sing Out The News" / Lyrics and Music by H. J. Rome., 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 34 cm. (Box 40, Folder 287)
    - [Southpaw] Music + Lyrics by Harold Rome. -- ca. 1967 Apr. 11., 1 manuscript score (78 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 41, Folder 288)
      Lists of orders of musical numbers and lyrics ([1] sheet; typescript) laid in
      Note: The Southpaw Deshons
      Contents [in order in which they were found]: The world is so rosy. Pretty Penny. What the game is all about. Only passing through. Again. The Washington fly. Which is which. Bruce William Pearson, Junior. Hall of fame. I lust for you. I'm gonna work your tails off. Apologizn' blues. A friend is a friend. They can't futz around. Love the game. Intro to love the game. Let's go Mammoths. Henry.
    - [Southpaw] The Southpaw / Harold Rome. -- 1967 May 10., 1 manuscript score (74 p. in various pagings); 31 cm. (Box 41, Folder 289)
      Signed note on folder: original mss. The Southpaw as completed May 10, 1967 Harold Rome
      Several numbers dated 1966
      Contents [in order in which they were found]: Love the game. What the game is all about. Pretty Penny. The world is so rosy. Again. Girls. Bruce William Pearson Jr. Hall of fame. I lust for you. Katie. Only passing through. A friend is a friend. I'm gonna work your tails off. Henry. They can't futz around. Love the game. Intro to love the game. Henry. Pistologione. Let's go mammoths! Bloody finger. The Washington fly! Which is which. Apologizn' blues
    - [Southpaw] Southpaw / Words and Music by Harold Rome. -- ca. 1969 Jan. 13., 1 manuscript score (74 p. in various pagings); 32 cm. (Box 41, Folder 290)
      Holograph, signed, in pencil and manuscript (photocopies) with pencil additions
      Includes lyrics ([29] sheets; typescript)
      Note on discarded folder: original mss. Southpaw Final Rewriting